SOPAN KHOSLA

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, 15213 412-370-3255 \$\displaysopank@andrew.cmu.edu \$\displaysopanding \displaysopanding \displaysop

PERSONAL SUMMARY

2+ years of industrial research experience spanning multiple research areas, 9 patents filed in the US and multiple publications in peer-reviewed conferences. Primary interests in problems related to natural language understanding (NLP), information extraction from medical records and conversations, dialog systems, and coreference resolution.

EDUCATION

CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY, PA, USA

August 2019 - Present

- MS, Language Technologies Institute
- GPA: 3.96
- Courses: 10-701 Machine Learning, 11-711 Algorithms for NLP, 11-747 Neural Networks for NLP, 80-816 Causal Learning

Indian Institute of Technology, Roorkee, India

July 2013 - June 2017

- B.Tech, Computer Science
- GPA: 9.43/10, Department Rank 3
- Director's Gold Medal for Outstanding All-round Achievement
- Courses: Data Structures and Algorithms, Artificial Intelligence, Advanced Graphical Networks, Data Mining

EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant, Carnegie Mellon University

August 2019 - Present

Working on information extraction and coreference resolution in medical dialogs, under the guidance of Prof. Carolyn Rose.

- Created a system that extracts medically relevant information from doctor-patient conversations. System leverages a multi-speaker BiLSTM for speaker-aware dialogue-modeling, and UMLS (a medical knowledge graph) for grounding raw text into medical concepts.
- Designed an architecture that uses semantic-type information to improve entity coreference resolution on state-of-the-art academic datasets.
- Spearheading the planning of a shared-task (competition) on anaphora and coreference resolution in dialog.

Research Engineer, Adobe Research India

July 2017 - July 2019

Worked on Natural Language Processing, Social Media Analytics and Marketing Research related projects.

- Used ML and NLP techniques for affect analysis on user-generated content (4 papers, 5 patents filed).
- Developed a technique to quantify latent customer experience from analytics clickstream data (2 papers, 2 patents filed).

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Python (including scikit-learn, pandas, numpy, Django etc.), Java, node.js, Javascript, React, PHP (Laravel), CSS
- Experience with ML frameworks like Pytorch, Tensorfow, and Keras.
- Data mining and cleaning, full-stack development, statistical data modeling

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS (Google Scholar)

- Sopan Khosla*, Rishabh Joshi*, Ritam Dutt*, Alan W. Black, and Yulia Tsvetkov. *LTIatCMU at SemEval-2020 Task 11: Incorporating multi-level features for multi-granular propaganda span identification.* SemEval Workshop at CoLing 2020 (4th rank in the shared-task). (* Joint First Authors)
- Kundan Krishna, **Sopan Khosla**, Jeffrey P Bigham, Zachary C Lipton. *Generating SOAP Notes from Doctor-Patient Conversations*. ArXiv Preprint 2020.
- Sopan Khosla, Niyati Chhaya, Shivam Jindal, Oindrila Saha, and Milind Srivastava. Do Events Change Opinions on Social Media? Studying the 2016 US Presidential Debates. In International Conference on Social Informatics, SocInfo 2019.
- Sopan Khosla*, Kushal Chawla*, and Niyati Chhaya. Gated Convolutional Encoder-Decoder for Semi-supervised Affect Prediction. In Pacific-Asia Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, PAKDD 2019. (* Joint First Authors)
- Atanu R. Sinha, Deepali Jain, Nikhil Sheoran, **Sopan Khosla**, and Reshmi Sasidharan. Surveys without Questions: A Reinforcement Learning Approach. AAAI 2019.
- Sopan Khosla, Niyati Chhaya, and Kushal Chawla. Aff2Vec: Affect-Enriched Distributional Word Representations. In Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, CoLing 2018.
- Sopan Khosla. EmotionX-AR: CNN-DCNN autoencoder based emotion classifier. In Proceedings of the Sixth International Workshop on Natural Language Processing for Social Media, ACL 2018 (Shared-Task Winner System).

RESEARCH INTERN, Adobe Research India

May 2016 - August 2016

Worked with the Big-data Intelligence Lab (BIL) at Bangalore, India and completed two independent projects:

- A method to characterize and score users on a publisher website based on their ad blocking tendency.
- A method to find effectiveness of anti ad-blocking strategies on publisher website (1 paper, 1 patent filed).

Software Engineering Intern, Google Summer of Code

May 2016 - August 2016

Worked as a Core Development Member of FOSSASIA.

- Created a frontend search application over <u>Loklak</u> API.
- Constructed rules for Susi, an AI based chat-bot built on Loklak.
- Created Wordpress plugins which integrate loklak support to different websites (Blog).

Research Intern, Symantec R&D Lab India

May 2015 - July 2015

Worked with the Digital Signing team at Bangalore, India.

- Developed a tool with an alternate workflow (alias Hash Signing) to digitally sign large files (size j. 2GB).
- Tool (integrated with Windows SignTool) increases the efficiency (by 100-1000X) as well as the security of document signing on cloud (1 patent filed).

RELEVANT COURSES

Machine Learning Algorithms for NLP Neural Networks for NLP Computational Semantics Causal Modeling Artificial Intelligence Design and Analysis of Algorithms Data Mining and Warehousing Object Oriented System Design

TEACHING AND RESPONSIBILITIES

Internship Mentor — Adobe Research

Mentored multiple students at Adobe Research over their summer research internships.

Mentor — Google Code-In

Mentored high-school students to contribute to FOSSASIA projects on github as part of the Google Code-In initiative.

Lecturer — IIT Roorkee

Organised multiple lectures on Data Structures, Object Oriented Design, Network Security, and Machine Learning for the students of IIT Roorkee.

CO-CONVENER WEB — Cognizance

Led the development of IIT Roorkee's annual tech-fest (Cognizance) website and supervised branding and social media advertising.

Secretary — SDSLabs

Head of administration and web-development at SDSLabs, a student-run technical group at IIT Roorkee.

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

$2017 \\ 2016$	IIT Roorkee (IITR) Director's Gold Medal for Outstanding All-round Achievement IITR Encore Award for All-round excellence
2016	IIT Roorkee Heritage Award Winner thrice, 2014-2016
2016	Microsoft Build The Shield National Champion
2015	Honda Young Engineer and Scientist Award
2015	Microsoft Code.Fun.Do. National finalist in 2015 and 2016
2014	Invited to Republic Day Parade, as a guest of PM of India
2013	All India Rank-7 in JEE-MAINS
2013	All India Rank-1 in CBSE 12th Board Examination (AISSCE)
2013	All India Rank-9 in National Science Talent Search Examination
2012	Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana (KVPY) Scholarship
2009	National Talent Search Examination (NTSE) Scholarship